Good afternoon, my followers.
I'm Esvarena de Sousa,
vice-president of Penajóia's
Residents' Association.
Penajóia is land owned by the IHRU
(state housing), where we built our homes.
Why did we build our houses
in this neighbourhood?
Because of the housing
crisis here in Portugal.
There is a housing crisis here
in Portugal, for those who don't know.
People often say we invaded,
did this and that, but in fact,
you don't know what's going on.
We were forced to build our houses here
because there's no housing,
as such, in Portugal.
We've been fighting the fight for housing.
We've been seeking an agreement
from the State itself, from the IHRU,
which owns the land.
We've petitioned the City Council,
we've sent many petitions to the IHRU,
we've sent many petitions to the State,
to see if they'll bring water
and electricity here for us to pay for.
We even want to pay property tax,
but neither the IHRU
nor the City Council take responsibility.
And we have no housing alternative,
because this
really is a situation
the Portuguese State itself is facing.
"Oh, you left your countries
and came here to build shacks."
We weren't the ones
who created the shacks.
Shacks have always existed in Portugal.
Every day that goes by,
more neighbourhoods spring up.
We've been fighting,
even without the State's support,
to improve our habitat,
our plots, our homes,
to get proper conditions.
But it's the State's own responsibility,
it's not up to us:
electricity, water and sanitation.
That's something the State
itself has to provide here.
As you can see,
the documents we sent to the City Council,
to see if they could give us,
or supply us,
let us benefit from these basic,
much-needed services.
Because it's also a form
of violence, isn't it?
It's violence against us.
We live like this, with no water,
no electricity, no basic sanitation.
This can't go on.
That's why I'm making this video,
to explain it to you.
To the many who keep saying
we want to live off handouts...
We want to live,
to build... We want handouts?
Nobody wants to live off handouts.
If we wanted handouts,
we'd be staying in shelters, wouldn't we?
We'd be staying in SOS homes.
Every month we try to improve the
conditions of the neighbourhood itself.
Since the State can't
build homes for everyone,
we build our own homes,
we spend money. So,
I think it would be common sense for the
State to bring water and electricity here.
So, we'll keep on fighting.
You'll be able to see the request
and also the City Council's reply.
Because the City Council
and the IHRU keep passing the buck.
Nobody takes responsibility. That's it.